<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Windsor before his Majesty, the second Sunday after Easter, 1684. by John Archbishop of Tuam.</title>
            <author>Vesey, John, 1636-1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B06421</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V282A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R185967</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">47012697</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 47012697</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174664</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B06421)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174664)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2694:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Windsor before his Majesty, the second Sunday after Easter, 1684. by John Archbishop of Tuam.</title>
                  <author>Vesey, John, 1636-1716.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Clavel ... and are to be sold by Samuel Helsham bookseller in Dublin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On t.p.: "Published by his Majesties special command."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Trinty College (Dublin, Ireland) Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LXXXII, 6-7 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174664:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174664:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> SERMON Preached at WINDSOR Before his Majeſty, the Second Sunday after Eaſter, 1684.</p>
            <p>By JOHN Archbiſhop of <hi>T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AM.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by his Majeſties ſpecial Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavel</hi> at the Peacock in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1684.</p>
            <p>And are to be ſold by <hi>Samuel Helſham</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Dublin</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:174664:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:174664:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached at <hi>WINDSOR.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 82. ver. 6, 7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>I have ſaid ye are gods, and all of you Sons of the Moſt High, but ye ſhall die like men.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe Holy Scriptures afford no where, a more ſolemn Charge and Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation unto Juſtice, than in the <hi>Pſalm</hi> whereof the Text is a part; from which be pleaſed to conſider, two things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. A full conceſſion of the great Dignity and Authority granted to <hi>Princes</hi> and Civil Rulers: <hi>I have ſaid ye are gods,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:174664:3"/>2. An Admonition of their being accountable for the Adminiſtration of it: <hi>But ye ſhall die like men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ye are <hi>gods,</hi> but ye are but <hi>mortal</hi> ones, of the ſame frail condition with thoſe your poor <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> that worſhip and adore your Power. When men are advanced to any height, their heads grow light and giddy, and they are too apt to deſpiſe thoſe below them, as of a ſmaller ſize and ſtature than themſelves. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dwells not on the intoxicating Argument of Power, but immediately calls down the thoughts of Princes from their <hi>golden heads,</hi> to conſider of their <hi>feet of Clay.</hi> He no ſooner wiſhes them joy of their Honour, but leſt their ſpirits ſhould be exalted above meaſure, and grow too fine and volatile, he fixes them with Grave-duſt, preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them with a Scepter and a Spade, the Royal Robes and a Winding-ſheet together: <hi>I have ſaid ye are gods, but ye ſhall die like men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before we conſider what is here ſaid, <hi>viz. Ye are gods,</hi> it may be proper to enquire, <hi>who</hi> it is that ſays, and <hi>to whom</hi> it is ſaid.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Who hath ſaid.</hi> Great Perſons have often this frailty among others, that though they moſt need, they can leaſt endure plain and wholſom inſtruction, the benefit whereof is often loſt, for want of Prudence in the Addreſs. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:174664:3"/> therefore to give weight and authority to what he ſays to the Princes of the World, perſonates the Almighty in the delivery of this charge, whom he places in the Throne,<note place="margin">Verſ. 1.</note> as a <hi>Judge among the Gods;</hi> not as an unconcerned Spectator, but as a ſevere Monitor, and Obſerver of their Actions, come down on purpoſe to take notice of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of that duty, which their high Titles and Commiſſions require of them. <hi>God ſtandeth in the Congregation of Princes.</hi> So that <hi>David</hi> doth not here uſurp an Authority over his Equals as a Reprover and Inſtructer, but with great ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Majeſty brings in God, as ſpeaking in his own name. So that this is emphatically Gods word that is here ſpoken; and ſo our Saviour ſays, referring to this Text,<note place="margin">Joh. 10.34.</note> 
               <hi>to whom the Word of God came.</hi> And where the Word of God is, there is Power with him in the ſupreme right of diſpoſal, who at firſt made all things, cloathed the World when it lay naked in its Cauſes and imperfect Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiality, and then ranged the various Orders and Claſſes of the Creation, according to the Idea's he had conceived in his eternal Mind; in which he hath ever ſince preſerved them by the breath of the ſame Power, which once diſconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, the Axes of the World would crack, and the whole Frame, like an old Houſe, would tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and fall in pieces. Since therefore all things do
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:174664:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo eſſentially depend upon him, he may well be preſumed to have a right to govern what he firſt raiſed out of nothing, and always maintains at his own charge, and to make what diſtinctions he pleaſes among the works of his own hands; on one piece of Clay putting the Image of a Prince, on another the Picture of a Beggar; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that to a noble, and this to an ignoble ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. So that things are and muſt be what he is pleaſed to call them: It is God that hath ſaid <hi>Ye are gods.</hi> But to whom doth he ſpeak? And that is the ſecond Enquiry?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>To whom is this ſaid?</hi> I have already ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed it to Princes and Civil Governours, though I am not ignorant that theſe words are challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged as the Churches Patrimony by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, in an Epiſtle to <hi>Mauricius</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. But if the Words were addreſſed to Church-men, it is plain from the ſtile of the <hi>Pſalm,</hi> it was in their Civil Relation and Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city. And all that can be inferred, is onely, that it was not then, nor is it now unlawful for an Eccleſiaſtical perſon to exerciſe Civil Power, when God and the King appoint them to it. But the Powers are in their natures diſtinct. And what was done by the <hi>High Prieſt</hi> under the Jewiſh <hi>Theocracy,</hi> muſt not be drawn into Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> for our Saviour affirms his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:174664:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Kingdom is not of this World,</hi> and hath thereby for ever diſcharged ſpiritual Perſons from tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Power, by virtue of their Office either di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly or in order to ſpiritual purpoſes; but he hath not made the man uncapable, by placing him at his Altar, of ſerving Princes <hi>in ſitting Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> when by them they are thereunto appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; nor is any Perſon leſs qualified, as one may think, for being the Kings Servant, for his ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, in ſome reſpects, nearer than others to <hi>Him, by whom Kings reign.</hi> And ſince a prudent and pious conduct of both Powers may make each promote the private ends of the other and the common end of both, the Glory of God, why ſhould they be thought ſo inſociable, as never to be exerciſed by the ſame Perſon? Nor indeed are they, by thoſe very men, who declare moſt againſt Church-mens <hi>medling,</hi> as they phraſe it, <hi>in Civil Affairs:</hi> for who are more forward in ſuch matters, when they have opportunity, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Authority, than ſuch as exclaim againſt our Church-men for thoſe Civil Truſts and Honours granted them by Authority? And while they preach againſt the exerciſe of a derived Power under Princes, are aſpiring after one paramount to them</p>
            <p>Princes are called <hi>Gods,</hi> and Miniſters are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Angels,</hi> let every one abide in that Calling
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:174664:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> wherewith he is called; for as that <hi>Prieſt or Angel</hi> that arrogates the Title of a <hi>God,</hi> ſmells ſtrong of the Pit, and ſavours of the Pride of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> ſo on the other ſide, they who condemn all Civil Power as unlawful in the Church, are too like <hi>Antichriſt</hi> indeed, <hi>Exalting themſelves above all that is called God</hi> in the State.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Having ſeen by, and to whom theſe words are ſpoken, let us now conſider the meaning of what is ſaid, <hi>Ye are gods, and all of you Children of the moſt High.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is on every Creature ſome Character of Divinity, but God hath placed his Image upon Man, impreſſed himſelf on our Nature, as the Prophet on the Child, and ſhed his likeneſs on us, ſo that by reflecting on our ſelves, we may know as in a Glaſs, and darkly, what God is: but as he hath honoured our <hi>Nature</hi> with his <hi>Image,</hi> part whereof was a Dominion over the Creation, ſo in our Nature he honours ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons with his <hi>Name,</hi> and hath thereby given them Dominion over others of their own kind. They have not onely his <hi>Image</hi> but <hi>Inſcription,</hi> of whom in a qualified ſenſe, we may ſay what they of <hi>Lycaonia</hi> ſaid of the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Acts 14.11.</note> 
               <hi>The Gods are come down unto us in the likeneſs of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I need not ſay here, they are not <hi>Gods and Sons of God,</hi> as our Saviour is, by an unconceivable ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:174664:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> which were to make them equal with God; <hi>To us there is but one God, though there be that are called Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor are they always Sons of God by Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption and Grace, as Members of the Inviſible Church; that Aphoriſm that <hi>Empire is founded in Dominion,</hi> being not more abſurd and falſe, than that other, that <hi>Dominion is founded in Grace.</hi> Grace neither giving title to Land and Eſtates, nor Eſtates to Empire. Wicked men may be not onely lawful Proprietors, but lawful and good Princes.</p>
            <p>Nor are Princes always laſtly, even by exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Profeſſion <hi>Sons of God,</hi> as viſible Members of the Church, though it is a great felicity when they and their ſubjects are ſo: no Crown ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſurer than ſuch as is moſt Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>For the true diſcovery therefore of that ſenſe in which they are ſtiled <hi>gods, and Sons of God,</hi> we muſt conſider, that it is familiar in Scripture to call a Perſon the Son of that man whom he reſembles in ſome very ſignal character; as <hi>Believers</hi> are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Sons of Abraham,</hi> for their reſemblance to him in that Grace, that was ſo eminent and illuſtrious in that Holy Patriarch, that it was <hi>imputed to him for Righteouſneſs.</hi> On the contrary, our Saviour ſaith to the Jews, Ye are of your <hi>Father</hi> the Devil, for the <hi>works</hi> of your Father the Devil you will
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:174664:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> do: ſuch as cruelty, and malice, and ſpight, and revenge, which argue a Diabolical nature and temper. Agreeably to this notion,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Princes are called Gods, becauſe as <hi>ſuch</hi> they have their being from God, that is, Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to govern.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe they reſemble God in the conduct and menage of that Authority they have from him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God calls them his Sons, becauſe as they are begotten by him, and are like him, ſo as a Father he defends them, and more eſpecially concerns himſelf in their cauſe and protection.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Princes have their Being from God, and are begotten by him: As in the Scale of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Genealogy,<note place="margin">Luke 3.</note> it is ſaid of all but <hi>Adam,</hi> he was the Son of ſuch a one, and he was the Son of ſuch a one, but of <hi>Adam, he was the Son of God,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he came immediately out of his hands. So may we ſay of inferiour Magiſtrates and Officers, who ſtand in ſubordination to others; but when we come to the Sovereign Power, that is the Iſſue of Heaven, they that are inveſted with it, are <hi>the Sons of God,</hi> of whom they hold imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, and are <hi>born of the ſeed of divine Authority and Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God who by his Word made the World, hath by the ſame Word, by ſaying <hi>Princes are Gods,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:174664:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> made them ſo, and this <hi>Scripture which cannot be broken,</hi> is their Commiſſion.<note place="margin">Joh. 10.35:</note> For ſo the Text is expreſly expounded by our Saviour, for he calls it, <hi>a Word of God coming</hi> to the Magiſtrate. Now we know the Word of God coming to a Perſon, is a Phraſe authorizing that Perſon to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice he is then imployed in. In the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>the Word of the Lord came unto me,</hi> is the common ſtile of the Prophets Order, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe words, <hi>Ye are gods,</hi> being a word com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto the Prince, are his Letters Patent for his Title and Authority.<note place="margin">Wiſd. 6.3, 4.</note> So that his <hi>Power is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lord, and Sovereignty of the Higheſt,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Wiſdom of Solomon,</hi> and <hi>by him Kings reign,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 8.15.</note> 
               <hi>and Princes decree Juſtice,</hi> ſaith the Wiſdom of God: Which Wiſdom acknowledges the Power even of <hi>Pilate</hi> over himſelf, and ſays,<note place="margin">Joh. 19.11.</note> 
               <hi>It was given him from above.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, the Powers that then were, <hi>the Powers that be,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>are ordained of God,</hi> though they were neither the moſt lawfully acquired nor the moſt equally adminiſtred. So that Magiſtracy and Magiſtrates, (for ſo the word <hi>Powers</hi> there, muſt be underſtood of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons exerciſing Power) are not onely of Gods general providence and permiſſion, which ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers many irregularities in the World, as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the abuſe of this Power by mal-admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, and ſometimes the ruine of it by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:174664:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> or Tranſlation by Conqueſt) but they are by his ſpecial <hi>ordination</hi> and appointment, <hi>they are ordained of God.</hi> And hence it is that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion is a <hi>damnable,</hi> and without true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>a damning ſin,</hi> and I fear it is in this, as well as other reſpects, as the ſin of Witchcraft, (the Covenant with Hell) that it is but too rarely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of.</p>
            <p>It is a fulſom thing to multiply Arguments and Authorities in a plain Cauſe, and ſuch is that, (if any) that I am pleading for, the divine Original of Government; which whoſo reads the Scriptures cannot but diſcern, unleſs he be <hi>haſtning after another God</hi> than they preach. But this truth will appear with fuller evidence, if we conſider the Riſes of Government, and what ſhare the <hi>People,</hi> that is, <hi>the governed part,</hi> can have in the moſt Popular Gonſtitutions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is certain that Government was origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in the <hi>Parents and Heads of Families;</hi> if we believe Mankind to have been created and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated according to the <hi>Scripture Tradition,</hi> which is the moſt natural and rational hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, and moſt credible, though it were not aſſiſted by Revelation. We could never yet find where that <hi>Utopia</hi> lies, where men lived without natural dependencies, but came into the World in Arms and Armour, fighting with, and deſtroying
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:174664:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> one another; and yet on ſuch precarious Poetick Fables, ſome have choſen to found their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths, rather than on the Hiſtory of the Bible, which informs us of another origination both of Men and of Society. There we are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with our growing from one common root, in the way of natural propagation, which ever carries a neceſſary obligation with it: for Nature teaches the Son obedience to the Father, ſo that <hi>Adam,</hi> were he now alive, would be the Univerſal Monarch by right of Nature, and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently in the language of the Text, <hi>Son of God, and of the Moſt High.</hi> And from him Power de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended to the firſt-born by the Priviledge of natural Succeſſion, without asking the conſent of his Brethren, and as the Family ſpread, ſo did the Empire. Marriages were made, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren begotten, and Houſes filled, and new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonies ſent out, and ſo by degrees a Tree became a Foreſt, and the Paternal Power ſpread and grew into a Political. This is the way and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod by which Government was firſt planted in one Family, and according to its increaſe, ſhed and diſſeminated it ſelf abroad over many, and ſo far there is no ſhadow of an Authority deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the People, that is, the governed part, unleſs we ſhould fancy the Root were made and nouriſhed of the Branches, and the Father of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:174664:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Children. But thus much of the Order of Nature, which was ſoon altered and broken in pieces by force.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For ſecondly, Men ſtill increaſing and multiplying, their natural Obligations of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to remoter Parents in the direct line, as well as love to Relations in the collateral, grew weaker and colder; and the farther the lines were drawn from the Centre, the further they were removed from one another; and ſo, as the <hi>Tree</hi> became a <hi>Foreſt,</hi> the Foreſt ſoon became a <hi>Wilderneſs.</hi> And then the Paſſions of Men were let looſe, and grew wild, and they began to range abroad, and to prey upon each others Poſſeſſions, and ſome grew <hi>Mighty Hunters,</hi> and by force or fraud drove their Neighbours into the toyl, and made them ſubmit to their Yoke and Tyranny, which they did not out of choice, but of neceſſity, as the Reed bends onely becauſe it is forced by the Storm, that otherwiſe would break it. I doubt not but it will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed me, that it is the <hi>Conquerours Sword</hi> that carves out <hi>what Right he hath,</hi> and not the Peoples courteſie and favour, which here is not ſuppoſed nor deſired, and I ſhall in return as readily yield, that <hi>meer Conqueſt</hi> gives no Right, nor lays any obligation on Peoples Conſciences to obey. There muſt be ſome Title antecedent (by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:174664:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> or particular divine Deſignation, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact) or a voluntary Submiſſion afterward at leaſt, to legitimate the Force, and entitle the Conquerour to a juſt Poſſeſſion. But if without theſe he have any Right, it is viſible it is without, and not from, but againſt the People and their Conſent. And thus much of Force and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God himſelf in his love and care for ſome portions of Mankind, hath not onely raiſed and qualified men that ſeem born for Government, but ſometimes immediately conferred a Title, or ſent a Prophet to anoint them. So <hi>Moſes, Joſhua</hi> and the Judges, and ſeveral Kings were ſet up by God, or a Prophet in his name; and on ſuch a Meſſage they aſcended the Throne, and ruled the People, without deſiring any ſuffrage from them, ſo as to derive their Title from it. <hi>Davids</hi> ſubſtantial right to the Crown, was his Unction and Divine Deſignation by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the Prophet <hi>Samuel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam, 16. V, 1. &amp; 13. 2 Sam. 2.3. 2 Sam. 5.3.</note> which the men of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> did ſeverally recognize in <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bron,</hi> by repeating of the Ceremony. The King further making a League with thoſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> before the Lord, that is, to govern by the Law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God had preſcribed by his Servant <hi>Moſes:</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> is an Act of Grace reſembled by the <hi>Coronat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Oath</hi> of our Kings, and not ſuch a ſtipulation b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:174664:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:174664:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:174664:10"/> 
               <hi>David</hi> and the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> as that a failure on his part ſhould devolve the Government upon them; for how ſhould that eſcheat to them, which he held not of them? his Right being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and antecedent to their ſubmiſſion. So then in this way of particular deſignation by God, no Right is derived from the People. If it be any Caſe, it is,</p>
            <p n="4">4. By Popular Election; when the People to prevent the miſchief of an evil Governour, or Uſurper, or the want of Government which in our lapſed State is the greateſt Evil of all, meet, chuſe ſuch a Perſon as they judge beſt qualified for the ends of Government, and inveſt him with all the Powers and Liberties, of which they were poſſeſſed by the Law of Nature, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging themſelves to defend his Perſon, and obey his Laws.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They elect the Perſon; but poſſibly they are not ſo free in this Action as they fanſie; will they exclude the Divine Providence, and allow God no ſhare in their Councils? Will they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine him to his own Heaven, and challenge the management of all Affairs here to themſelves? We are neither ſuch automatous Machines as move onely as we are ſet and directed; nor ſuch abſolute Lords of our Actions, as we imagine our ſelves; we cannot bring about always cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:174664:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> what we freely deſign, but God often ſteps between the purpoſe and the event: and at other times addreſſes our free motions by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen hand: So that the People may name the Perſon, but God chuſes, he ſpeaks by their voice, and acts by their hands;<note place="margin">Pſal. 75.7.</note> for he is the <hi>Judge that putteth down one, and ſetteth up another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. When the Prince is elected, the People in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt him with Power, that is, with all they have, and more they cannot give. But there is a Power neceſſary to Government, which the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple never had, and therefore could not give; that is, of puniſhing capitally, which the Prince either uſurps, or derives from ſome higher Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple. So that the People can onely make a <hi>Golden Calf, or an Idol, but not a God:</hi> If the Prince had no Power but from them, the Government would be weak, and inſufficient for the ends of it; for without Capital puniſhment he could not be a <hi>terrour to Evil doers:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> But the People ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had this Power, (I mean the governed part) radically in them, becauſe no man ever had it ſingly, before Government was ſetled. No man hath more power over another in the State (or Notion rather) of Nature, than over him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. But no man hath a right to diſpoſe of his own life; he cannot kill himſelf without ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and therefore he cannot have, as a private
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:174664:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> perſon, this right over another; and if he have not this right in himſelf over himſelf, neither can he transfer it to another: and if one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, neither can two, nor three, nor any number; for Number may give <hi>Force</hi> but no <hi>Right:</hi> if an hundred ſet on one man and kill him without Authority, it is as much murder, as if but one had done it. To ſum up this therefore.</p>
            <p>Men embodying into a Society, and ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to one perſon or more, part onely with what they have, their Liberties and Poſſeſſions, but over their Lives having no right, they can make no diſpoſal; and therefore the exerciſe of this Power in the Prince can be no iſſue from the People, (for then the Stream muſt run higher than the Spring) but from God, whoſe Prerogative it is both to give Life, and to take it away, and not to be challenged by any perſon, <hi>(for Vengeance is mine)</hi> but to whom he commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicates it. And therefore the Prince ſtrikes with Gods Sword, and the Apoſtles Expreſſion is very accurate,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> when he ſays, he is <hi>the Miniſter of God, an Avenger for wrath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am not ignorant that the whole ſeries and Scale of Magiſtracy, (as well the <hi>King as Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme, as Governours ſent by him</hi>) is called by the Apoſtle, <hi>a humane Creature,</hi> to whom yet he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joins ſubjection,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.13.</note> for the <hi>Lords ſake,</hi> as the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:174664:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the Authority. <hi>Men</hi> may be Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Election, and the ſafety of <hi>Humane Society</hi> may be the end of their choice, on which accounts the Government is there called, a <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Ordinance,</hi> which in its Original, is the <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> As a City may elect a Mayor by priviledge of Charter, but his Authority when elected, is from the King, ſo is the Kings from God, where the People have the greateſt ſhare viſibly in the Deſignation of the perſon: but they onely prepare and diſpoſe the matter in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical Generation, but the Soul of Sovereignty is Divine, and infuſed from above, and not by low and popular traduction, if you conſider Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to take its Riſe either from the Order of Nature, or from Conqueſt, or particular De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation, either Divine or Humane. And ſo much may ſuffice for the firſt Reaſon why Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are called <hi>Gods, and Sons of God,</hi> they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by him.</p>
            <p>I have herein poſſibly made too bold with your patience, though the temper of this Age be too juſt an Apology for my doing ſo. But <hi>if ye ſuffer Fools</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, but I know not how) <hi>gladly;</hi> if every Journeyman become a Kings Monitor, and every Pebble in the Guttur thinks it ſelf a Jewel worthy of their Crowns, or the Breſts of Prieſts, there to ſhine and riſe up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:174664:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Oracles,</hi> ſuffer us alſo in the diſcharge of what we owe to Religion and our Sovereign, to tire you a little on ſo neceſſary a Doctrine, and ſuch Inferences as fairly flow from it; As</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Prince deriving his Authority from God, it follows hence, he is accountable to none but God. <hi>He ſtands or falls to his own Maſter, and he calls no man Maſter upon Earth.</hi> This is truly in right reaſon a conſequence from the Nature and End of Government. There muſt be ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons (according to the Frame of the Polity) from whom there muſt be no Appeal. <hi>Some Authority muſt be abſolute and injuſticiable,</hi> or the Proceſs will be infinite, and the Grievance with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Remedy; and the circular and endleſs moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Appeals, more grievous than any Tyranny.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the Prince derive his Authority from God, it follows again, <hi>His Laws oblige the Conſcience of the Subject:</hi> Such as command lawful things, for to an unlawful thing there can be no obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe he hath no authority from God to make unjuſt Laws, and therefore if he doth, they do not oblige the Conſcience of the Subject to that obedience, which is called active, though even in ſuch caſes, he is obliged to ſubjection, to endure the penalty, which they call paſſive obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p>But if the matter of the Command be a thing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:174664:12"/> indifferent, not forbidden by any Law of God, Moral, or Poſitive, there the Prince creates an obligation in Conſcience to conformity and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. For men to think they muſt have the ſame liberty after they are entered into Society, either Civil or Religious, as before, is contrary to the very nature and end of Society: they muſt ſubmit themſelves in things lawful to the determination of the Communion, whereof they become Members; and the enquiry lies not, whether the thing enjoined be expedient or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expedient, for of that the governing part muſt judge, but onely whether it be lawful. And it is lawful, if not forbidden by God; and if lawful before, it becomes now after the Law neceſſary in its uſe, and ſo is our obedience. Nor doth this take away the natural indifferency of the thing, nor the liberty of Chriſtians, nor exalt Princes into Gods Throne, or make them Lords of Conſcience, (for that is ſtill free to judge of the natural indifferency) any more than our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation in Conſcience to believe what the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles have delivered, makes them <hi>Lords of our Faith;</hi> a Title which they diſclaimed, as proper to him who is the <hi>Author and Finiſher of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Princes are called Gods, not onely becauſe he begets them, but they are like God in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of their power. Which is a reaſon
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:174664:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> aſſigned by <hi>Hierocles,</hi> why the <hi>Heroes</hi> were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led alſo the Sons of God in the Ethnick Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy. Now Princes reſemble God when they act by the ſame principle, and for the ſame end.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In making their Juſtice ſhine with equal diſpenſation on the Righteous and the Wicked; and not onely in doing, but in loving of Juſtice. This carries a double benefit with it to him that ſues for it, and him that diſtributes it. The love of Juſtice ſweetens the toil of the Employment, and makes that a Recreation, which without it is a Drudgery; for <hi>it is a joy to the Juſt to do judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Princes reſemble God in Mercy. This is the firſt letter of the Name, whereby God proclaims himſelf to <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 34.6.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord, the Lord God, Merciful and Gracious, &amp;c.</hi> and herein he is principally to be imitated by ſuch as are <hi>called by his Name,</hi> in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derating the rigour of Law, when men in their ſimplicity and honeſt meaning, may fall within the laſh of its ſeverity: or <hi>when the face of the Poor is ground, and eaten up like Bread,</hi> by the greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of an Oppreſſor. It is impoſſible but there ſhould be frequently ſuch caſes, wherein if the Letter of the Law be ſtrictly obſerved, the end will not; and it is the Glory of a Prince in ſuch caſes to extricate perſons out of the ſnares of le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Entanglements, and his Prerogative is then
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:174664:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> much more advantageous to his Subjects, than all their boaſted priviledges.</p>
            <p>I need not ſay on this occaſion, what Prince of the World is the moſt lively Image of this moſt Heavenly Attribute, whoſe <hi>Mercy,</hi> like the Divine Original, is indeed <hi>over all his Works,</hi> who makes not every man an <hi>Offender for a Word,</hi> nor every Offence Capital, but is <hi>ſtrong and patient, though provoked every day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Princes are like God, when they act, as by the ſame principles of Juſtice and Mercy, ſo for the ſame end and ſafety of the Society. They are therefore elſewhere ſtiled <hi>Reſtorers of Paths, and Healers of Breaches,</hi> and here the bleſſing of the <hi>Peace-makers</hi> falls upon their heads, which ſaith our Saviour is to be called <hi>the Sons of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.9.</note> and the more they intend this God-like end, in preſerving the peace, not only of their own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, but of the World in general, the better title they have to that <hi>Beatitude,</hi> and nearer reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance to the God of Peace. There are indeed ſome Sons, not very like their Father, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the great <hi>Deſtroyer</hi> rather, <hi>that is daily ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whom he may devour.</hi> Such are Diſciplines and Scourges in the hand of God, (as one of the Gothick Kings called himſelf) to chaſtiſe the Chriſtian World for their Luxury and contempt of God and his Commandments. But though
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:174664:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> theſe are onely ſtimulated with the Luſt of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, yet they are over-ruled by the Divine Providence, and directed to a point they thought not of, and often forced to bring Glory to God in the concluſion, though they deſigned onely their own, in the firſt motion of their Arms. But what ever exceſſes the wantonneſs of Power may tempt ſome Spirits to, they have the beſt right to this high Title of being the <hi>Sons of God</hi> and are the moſt natural Lords of their People, who like <hi>Parents, are always laying up for their Children,</hi> eſteeming their peace a common advantage, the Glory of their Reign, as the publick Good of the World is the Glory of God.</p>
            <p>There is certainly great truth in that celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Aphoriſm, <hi>Salus Populi Suprema Lex eſto;</hi> but the vulgar ſenſe is to be corrected by conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what is meant by <hi>People, Safety, and Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We are not to preſcind the Head from the Members, but by <hi>People</hi> to underſtand the whole Body, all <hi>in,</hi> as well as all <hi>under</hi> Government. And ſo indeed the care ought to be mutual and reciprocal, for neither can be ſafe, when the other is in danger; but the principal ſhould be for the principal and vital parts, and the beſt Armour placed on the Head and Heart. Thus while <hi>David</hi> perceived his <hi>Kingdom to be exalted for the ſake of Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 5.12. &amp; 21.17.</note> the People called him <hi>the light
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:174664:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> of Iſrael,</hi> which they were fearful ſhould be <hi>quenched.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. We are not to underſtand <hi>Safety</hi> in the moſt uncircumſcribed and indefinite ſenſe, for Peace of any kind, on any terms; but ſuch as the Apoſtle preſcribes, which by Prayer for Princes, we may hope to enjoy under them,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>a quiet and a peaceable life, in all godlineſs and honeſty.</hi> Now happy are the People that are in ſuch a caſe; this is a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing greatly deſirable, a Reformation heartily to be endeavoured, when Peace, and Godlineſs, and Honeſty meet together and kiſs each other.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Peace and Safety</hi> thus deſcribed is the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Law,</hi> that is, the general Rule and Canon of Direction to all in their reſpective Stations, it is the Princes <hi>Reaſon of State,</hi> the Compaſs by which he ſteers the Government, where plain and poſitive Law hath not directed; and where it hath, he muſt often leap over, nay break through many poſitive Forms to come at it; for that is the Supreme Law, to which all poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Laws, as inferiour, muſt give place; for the ſake of that, the Prince may diſpence with theſe, but that is indiſpenſable, it is ſuperiour to him in a way of perpetual direction, which he is the moſt proper Judge how to intend and follow. This Law alſo is the Square and Reaſon of the Subjects obedience, by which and Prayer they
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:174664:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:174664:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:174664:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> are more likely to obtain their end, than by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion and Schiſm; that being a method of Gods appointing, but this an unſanctified way that never will be bleſſed by him. Thus you ſee this ſo applauded Maxim is far from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding Government, by making Rulers ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to thoſe they Govern; that the Right to Govern is from the People, (if you divide the Head from the Body) becauſe their Good is the and of Government, is a falſe Inference from a falſe Principle, the preſervation of the whole is the end, and not of any part; and if the good and ſafety of the People (ſeparately from the Prince) were the Supreme Law, yet it follows not, that either his Right is derived from them, or his account of the Adminiſtration muſt be made to them. For God hath the ſame end, the Common Good, in the great Monarchy of the World, and yet is not liable to an Indictment by his Subjects for any mal-adminiſtration. And Parents and Maſters of Families intend the ſame end in their petty Monarchies, and are not queſtionable or puniſhable by their Children. So that this cannot give Subjects any ſuperin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendency over the Princes Councils or Actions, but obliges them rather in their private capacity of Obedience and Religion to conſpire to the ſame end, the Glory of God, in the Publick
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:174664:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> Good. Both theſe are deſigned by God, and both by the Prince, and the diſtinction is rather formal than real between them: for though they may be diſtinguiſhed, they cannot be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but are to be promoted by the ſame means. God cannot be honoured by Sin, and therefore <hi>we muſt not do evil that good may come of it.</hi> God may ſuffer it for that end, but we muſt not do it for that or any end. No more muſt publick Safety and common Good be ſecured by any thing that is unjuſt or diſhoneſt. Religion muſt not be reformed by Rebellion, nor deſtroyed for the ſake of a palliated worldly Peace. The very Heathens were ſo generous, as to ſcorn by baſe Compliances and wicked Plots and Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems to preſerve their Country; and therefore a contrivance of <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> for the publick Good being imparted to <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> was rejected by the Senate upon <hi>Ariſtides</hi> his Report, that it was not honeſt, concluding nothing profitable or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, that was diſhoneſt; but when the common Good is carried on by juſt and wiſe Counſels, a peaceable life is endeavoured by pious and honeſt policy, the People have at once great ſafety, and God great Glory; and this is the care and travel Princes have under the Sun, to be in continual motion, that their Subjects might have the comfort of their Influences,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:174664:17"/> though they are too often requited with noiſom ſtenches and ſtinking exhalations. But as God is never weary of doing good to thoſe who weary him and themſelves with doing evil; ſo neither ſhould Princes, though their Subjects prove ungrateful and rebellious. Thus much of the ſecond Reaſon why Princes are called <hi>Gods, and Sons of God,</hi> they are like him, acting the ſame Attributes, and for the ſame end.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly and laſtly, They are ſo called, becauſe God as a Father takes a ſpecial care of juſt Governments and pious Governours. There are ſometimes Providences that ſeem anomalous and exceptions from this Rule, when God ſuffers Religious Kings to be ſmitten by and for the ſins of the People, which is one of the heavieſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that can befal a Nation, to be made their own Executioners, by cutting the throat of their own peace and happineſs. But as Princes are called Fathers of their Country, and have bowels for their Subjects, ſo hath God for Princes, whoſe Seats could never be ſo ſecure, <hi>amidſt ſo many ſtrivings of the People, but that the Lord is King be the Earth never ſo unquiet, and covers the head of his Anointed, and bears up the Pillars of his Throne.</hi> So we find, notwithſtanding all the Plots, the ſecret Caballings, and open and bold Deſigns of <hi>Davids</hi> Enemies,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> God ſays, <hi>Yet have I ſet my King upon my
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:174664:17"/> holy Hill of Sion,</hi> exalted him to the top of Regal Power. God ſeems to point at him with a hand out of the Clouds, as a perſon reſerved for ſome great work, and by his miraculous delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, eminently to declare him to be his <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Darling, Thou art my Son,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>this day have I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten thee.</hi> Which Scripture, though it had a literal verification in <hi>David,</hi> and a myſtical one in our Saviour, may be accommodated to the Hiſtories of other Empires, and no where more fitly than to the modern ſtate of this Kingdom; in the ſupport whereof the Divine Providence hath obſervably concerned it ſelf, <hi>when all the foundations of the Earth were out of courſe,</hi> and like the Earth our Government ſeemed to hang with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any hold. <hi>But though God be terrible among other Kings of the Earth,</hi> and is now <hi>daſhing them in pieces, like a Potters Veſſel,</hi> he hath <hi>ſet ours upon his holy Hill of Sion;</hi> where may the ſame Goodneſs long and long preſerve him.</p>
            <p>That what hath been ſaid may be made uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Since Princes are called <hi>Gods,</hi> it would be their care <hi>to walk worthy of that high calling,</hi> and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour their own Character, by defending his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Worſhippers from Contempt, that hath
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:174664:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo honoured them; neither ſuffering their Power to degenerate into Cruelty or Tyranny, for that were of <hi>Gods</hi> to become <hi>Devils,</hi> nor their zeal for Juſtice and Religion, into Sloth and Lukewarmneſs and Neutrality; for that were to become <hi>Idols,</hi> that have eyes and ſee not, ears and hear not: for then the latter part of the Text will appear like the writing on the Wall to <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> in the height of all his jollity. When the ſwelling Titles fume in the head, and they are elevated (like Alexander) with vain thoughts of being really what they are onely called, God will call them to account, who hath ſaid, <hi>they ſhall die like men,</hi> and there will be no diſtinction in the Grave, the Crown will leave no impreſſion on the Scull. But let us leave them to be chaſtized by him againſt whom onely they ſin; and</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the next place conſider what ſhall be done to them whom God hath ſo honoured, as to give them <hi>a Name above every Name? Surely they will reverence my Son,</hi> ſaith God in the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: and ſurely ſo we ſhould. But alas! to the reproach of the Chriſtian Name, both that which calls her ſelf <hi>the Holy and the Catholick,</hi> and many that would be thought the <hi>True Proteſtant and Reformed Church,</hi> have eaten of <hi>ſower Grapes,</hi> and their Childrens Teeth are ſet on edge:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:174664:18"/> while both Revile and Crucifie our Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, that ſo ſincerely preaches and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes the Doctrine of Loyal Obedience, that let a Prince be of any Religion, as to his private Faith, it would be his Intereſt to have all his Subjects of that, of the eſtabliſhed Church of <hi>England.</hi> I ſhall crave leave to ſpeak a little to thoſe of each hand, though I fear I ſhall <hi>become their Enemy becauſe I tell them the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nothing is more current in the <hi>Court of Rome,</hi> than the Doctrine of the Popes Supremacy over Princes; it is the <hi>Teſt</hi> of Roman Orthodoxy. This is acknowledged by many, who yet will not allow it the Doctrine of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> and I wiſh for my own part, it were not.</p>
            <p>But what is that they call the <hi>Court of Rome?</hi> The Pope and Conclave, and their Retinue of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſts, and other Expectants of Preferment. And what is the Church? The Pope and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council. In both which this Doctrine is ſo plainly taught, that it is hard to tell which is the <hi>Mother</hi> of the Child. To Quote particular Authors were an endleſs labour. <hi>Aquinas</hi> rules the Caſe for the School, and in <hi>Bellarmine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aqu. 22. q. 12. a. 2. Bell. Rom, Pont. l. 5, c. 8. 9. Val. tom. 3. diſp. 1. qu. 12. punct. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia,</hi> and many others, we have the Uſage and Practice of the Court, in the Catalogues of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces depoſed; from whence they argue this may
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:174664:19"/> be done, becauſe it hath been; but the Hiſtory is better than the Logick. But that which is chiefly conſiderable, is the Canon of the Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. Council of Lateran, ch 3.</note> which in point decrees <hi>ſuch Princes as will not expel Hereticks out of their Dominions, to be Excommunicated, and their Subjects abſolved from their Allegiance, and their Kingdoms to be given to Catholick Princes.</hi> There is a <hi>Salvo</hi> for the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Lord, if he obſtruct not the Sentence, (that is, they will not depoſe him, if he ſubmits) like the Condition in the <hi>Covenant</hi> to fight for the King, if he would fight for it. If it be ſaid, this is a part of the <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> and not the <hi>Faith</hi> of the Church, the matter is not much mended, nor Princes better ſecured by the diſtinction, ſince we know they are as rigid exacters of Obedience to the Rule of Diſcipline as of Faith. But thus by their Canon of Diſcipline they make void the Law of the Fifth Commandment, diſcharging Subjects of their Duty to thoſe whom God and Nature hath commanded them to honour and obey.</p>
            <p>Now this Council (if any) deſerves with them the name of General, conſiſting of 1215 Fathers (one for every Year from Chriſts Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity to the Year of its Aſſembling) Convened and Confirmed by the Popes Authority, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:174664:19"/> is accordingly owned as ſuch, even by two ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding General Councils, <hi>Conſtance</hi> and <hi>Trent:</hi> in the mouth of which two Witneſſes,<note place="margin">Conſt. Seſſ. 30. Trid. Seſſ. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cap. 5.</note> (whereas <hi>Trent</hi> bears onely witneſs to it ſelf) the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of this Council is more than abundantly confirmed.</p>
            <p>The Iſſue is this:
<list>
                  <item>1. A General Council declares the Doctrine of the Church.</item>
                  <item>2. The Fourth of <hi>Lateran</hi> is a General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, in the judgment of thoſe of <hi>Conſtance</hi> and <hi>Trent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. That hath decreed the Depoſing of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, if they expel not Hereticks, after admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, out of their Dominions; this then is the Doctrine not of Jeſuits onely, their Order be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing founded ſome Centuries after; nor of the Court, but even of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And yet I would not accuſe all that hold Communion with it of an explicit belief of this Doctrine: there are many whoſe Loyalty is ſo ſound and healthy, that it is not to be tainted by the peſtilential Air they breath in, who would deſert that Church in which they believed ſuch things were taught. Such I onely deſire nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to believe our Prieſts who charge them with it, nor their own who deny it, till, like thoſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:174664:20"/> 
               <hi>Noble Bereans,</hi> they have conſulted their own Editions of their Councils, their Eyes, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Senſe, and then they will diſcern by whom they are abuſed, and of what <hi>Leven they are to take heed and beware.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. But while I am ſpeaking of theſe things, methinks I hear a Voice, ſaying unto me, as unto the Prophet,<note place="margin">Ezek. 8.6.</note> 
               <hi>Son of man, ſeeſt thou what they do,</hi> they of the Church of <hi>Rome, turn thee yet again, and thou ſhalt ſee greater abominations:</hi> a People as diſtant from the Papiſts, as one Pole from the other, in the intereſt, yet parallel with them, in the miſchief of their Faction, who pretending to be <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> have whet their Swords among the Philiſtins, and entered into the ſecret of our Adverſaries. Thoſe men in their zeal for God, rebel againſt his Authority, and ſerve their Prince as the Heathens were thought to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <hi>Mercury,</hi> by throwing Stones at him; in kindneſs to the Reformation, they ſtab it to the heart, and under <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſmooth voice, make it feel the rough hands of <hi>Eſau;</hi> endeavouring to deſtroy at once, the beſt Government, the beſt Monarchy, and Monarch, and Religion in the World.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The beſt Government; A Monarchy, the firſt and moſt natural Form: a Form that hath
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:174664:20"/> the faireſt pretence, (to ſpeak modeſtly) to a Divine Right. Others may be lawful, but God never immediately appointed any other Form. <hi>Moſes was King in Jeſurun.</hi> The Government of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> till <hi>Saul,</hi> was Theocracy, the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt kind of Monarchy. So this Government is beſt, as approved of God, under which the greateſt bleſſings are promiſed to his Church of Kings becoming Nurſing Fathers; beſt in its ſelf, as moſt ſufficient and ready for the ends of Government, and beſt for us, as moſt agreeable to the Genius of theſe Nations, who would never long endure many Tyrants.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The beſt Monarchy, whereby the gracious Conceſſions of our Kings, and harſhneſs of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Power is ſweetned into a Fatherly tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and <hi>Will</hi> is changed into <hi>Law,</hi> and the Rod of Iron is melted down into a Golden Scepter; and it is the true Intereſt of the People to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Prerogative, becauſe that doth beſt preſerve the Liberties of the People. We have in our Conſtitution all the advantages of others, without the Inconveniences that attend them. And all others, of what Form ſoever, are abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and arbitrary, fierce as the Wind, and hot as the fire, while God ſpeaks to us, in this, <hi>in a gentle and a ſtill voice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:174664:21"/>3. The beſt Monarch. But while <hi>my heart is inditing of a good matter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 45.1.</note> 
               <hi>and I would ſpeak of the things, I have made of the King,</hi> his Royal preſence hinders <hi>my tongue from being the Pen of a ready Writer,</hi> and forbids me to ſpeak either of his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal or Political Endowments, the gentleneſs and goodneſs of his <hi>Nature</hi> or his <hi>Royal</hi> Virtues. In ſtead therefore of ſuch an Entertainment, let us rejoice in the cool ſhade of thoſe Bleſſings we enjoy under his Protection, and take a view of the flouriſhing condition theſe Kingdoms are in, did they think themſelves ſo. In whoſe Reign did the Sun ever behold this People ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in greater wealth, the Trade and Riches of the World flowing in to their Doors? We are tilling our Fields, and filling our Barns and Store-houſes, while our Neighbours Backs are ploughed and harrowed by the miſeries of War. We are groaning onely under the burden of Peace, panting under loads of Plenty, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting of Health, and running into Fevers through height and abundance of Bloud. To conclude, nothing is wanting to us, but thankful hearts for ſuch Bleſſings, as no Nation under Heaven doth or can enjoy, but under ſuch a Monarchy and Monarch.</p>
            <p n="4">4. What ſhall I ſay of our Religion, which is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:174664:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> our higheſt Glory; for <hi>God hath not dealt ſo with any Nation as with us.</hi> If we were not become too brutiſh to have a reliſh for ſo ſpiritual a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, you might be even charmed to Exta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, with the proſpect of the Heavenly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts you enjoy above all others in the World, in a Church Orthodox in her Faith, Chaſt in her Worſhip, Modeſt, yet Solemn in her Ceremony, Primitive in her Government, General and Peaceable in her Articles of Communion, Gentle in her Diſcipline, Charitable to perſons of honeſt lives, though differing perſuaſions in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Faith, and more than any other, Loyal to Princes. I wiſh we might be provoked to jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie by another of the ſame Beauty. This is the Hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> the Joy of the Earth, upon which God hath ſet his King; and of theſe Bleſſings theſe men would rob us, and expoſe us a naked prey to our cruel Enemies, deſtroy the <hi>Laws</hi> to ſecure our Eſtates, and our <hi>Religion</hi> to ſave our Souls. In return of all which, I hear her crying out in the words, and with the tears and compaſſion of our Saviour, <hi>O Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem, thou that killeſt my Prophets, how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, &amp;c.</hi> Oh ye of the Foreign Reformation how often would I have gathered you under the Wings of my Communion, and covered, or excuſed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:174664:22"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:174664:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:174664:23"/> your defects, and ye would not; but now theſe things are hid from your eyes, <hi>and your houſe is left unto you deſolate.</hi> And Oh ye of the Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick ſeparation, how often would I have ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered you? but ſo often <hi>have I ſtretched forth my hands to a diſobedient and gainſaying People.</hi> Yet at laſt return to a Chriſtian peaceful temper, for <hi>ye know not what ſpirit ye are of;</hi> it is your Schiſm that is like to open the Poſtern for the common Enemy of the Reformation; 'tis under your co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert he hides his Spies and Intelligencers, through your Diviſions the Name of Proteſtant is evilly ſpoken of, and our Brethren abroad are the worſe treated, for the weakneſs that you occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion at home. Conſider therefore your duty and the common danger, and <hi>kiſs the Son leſt ye periſh, and pray for the man of Gods right hand, that he would make him ſtrong for himſelf, and while he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours for Peace, make not your ſelves ready for the Battel;</hi> and then the God of Peace will return, ſtabliſh, ſtrengthen, ſettle us. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:174664:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
